<Document>
  # Equipment and Personnel Standards

    These are sets of regulations and policies that govern the use of equipment and standards of appearance for military personnel.

  ## Standard Issue Equipment
    - Standard issue equipment is defined as any military or police uniform, armour, weapon, or accessory personnel find in their vendors, as well as anything they awake with or respective armoury (s).
    - The Acting Commander may issue special equipment on a case-by-case basis, such as special headsets or special weaponry for certain personnel or units, as long as it does not violate the UCMJ or SOP.
    - Alcohol must be stored in the officers' mess or an officer's office(s).

  ## Uniform Regulations
    Personnel are required to wear appropriate clothing during operations. SOP may not be changed to allow personnel to deploy without clothes or a uniform.
      - Intelligence officers and intelligence technicians, with the commander's permission, may exempt themselves from all uniform regulations in relation to wearing military clothing, boots, headwear and weaponry.
      - Deploying personnel must be wearing their uniform, boots and chest protective armour at a minimum. Suit webbings may be used in the place of chest protective armour.
      - All personnel required to wear armour at all times may temporarily remove it while on a friendly ship and/or installation or after an operation has ended for social events, such as memorials. Other forms of clothing, like service jackets, may be used during this time.
      - All personnel must wear their uniform and assigned footwear or a standard-issue replacement.
      - Auxiliary staff and support crew should not be in armour unless the ship/base is on a security alert or is deploying to the AO.
      - MP/Law Enforcement, combat personnel and flight crew are permitted to wear armour on the ship/installation, as part of their job.
      - Any headwear that is worn must be standard issue or an acceptable replacement. Exceptions must be made for reasonable religious headdress
      - Anyone of higher rank may still order any personnel below them to wear a protective helmet or vest unless they are a rifleman who has not been issued a special weapon.
      - Folding or otherwise shortening uniforms is permitted, provided no damage comes to the uniform.
      - Dress uniforms may be worn by shipside staff as long as they are not deploying.

  ## Firearm Handling Regulations
    - Weapons should be holstered or slung when not in use and with the safety engaged. Personnel must be allowed to holster or sling their weapons on their first offence.
    - Under normal circumstances, weapons may only be fired in the firing range. (Unless for ceremonial or briefing purposes)
    - Training equipment like training grenades and training ammunition must only be used in firing ranges.
    - Weapons may not be left unattended unless properly secured in spaces intended for them, like weapon racks or cabinets.
    - If no firing range is available, MPs may be asked to designate a temporary safe area for weapons to be discharged.
    - All shipside staff, aside from Flight Crew and Military Police, are to remain armed with only a sidearm, only arming with long arms if the ship/installation is in danger.

  ## Medical Regulations
    - All pills are to be stored within a sealed container and properly labelled with either a pill dosage max before overdose or the number of units the pill provides.
    - All loose chemicals, if it were to contain anything other than water or welding fuel, are to be properly labelled with what it contains as well as the max dosage to avoid overdose.

  ## Synthetic Operations
    - Synthetics are not at any point authorised to wield a firearm; synths may hold firearms in one hand for transport or safety reasons.
    - Synthetics are allowed to carry knives, tools, and other similar equipment if needed to function in their job at optimal levels.
    - Synthetics may conduct arrests freely when a crime has been committed, but are not allowed to sentence the arrested individual.
    - Synthetics are specialised in all tasks and are expected to carry them out at exceptional levels. Synthetics may be specialised in a specific task, such as military police, but may not neglect other tasks.
    - Synthetics may be sent to their manufacturer for examination if a representative or alike is on or near the installation. If the unit's user manual says not to allow access by other companies, it must be respected.
    - Synthetics may not be used in place of ship staff for deployment purposes; for example, if a member of the medical staff is awake, they must be shipside, and the synthetic can deploy.
    - Synthetics are required to ensure Medical and Brig are maintained in the absence of any medical or military police staff.
    - Synthetics may perform operations alone so long as it does not violate their core directives of self-preservation. 

  ## Use of language
    Military personnel may be trained in a wide variety of languages and be able to speak and understand them. However, there are restrictions on where this is acceptable and where it is not.
      - Briefings, Debriefings, memorial, and any other formal events are to occur with everyone speaking the unit’s primary language.
      - Orders from command staff, tactical planning and, in general, any operation-related tasks are to be held in the unit’s primary language.
      - Any form of social gathering, RNR, before a briefing or during non-combat scenarios, anyone may use whatever languages they can speak and understand

  ## AI Core and Synthetic Areas
    The AI Core and Designated Synthetic Areas are restricted from public access and may only be entered with permission from a Synth, Working Joe, CO, EO or the AI Core.
      - Entering the AI Core or Synthetic Area without permission is chargeable as trespassing
      - Synthetics and Working Joes are permitted to dismiss anyone causing a disturbance
      - If a person fails to leave the area within 3 chances given by Synthetics or Working Joes, non-lethal force may be used
      - If a person shows an active threat in these areas to a Synthetic, Working Joe, or the AI Core, lethal force may be used by the stated groups.

  ## Grooming Standards
    - Personnel must maintain a professional and operationally safe hairstyle while on duty.
    - Hair may be worn down to the shoulders in a bob or similar style, but must be tied back if it extends any longer.
    - Tied-back hair, such as ponytails, may extend to the small of the back but must not exceed that length or wrap around to the front.
    - Facial hair is permitted but must not extend below the neckline or past the face in any direction.
    - Hair must be of a natural colour.
    - Squad Leaders, members of command staff and Military Police can enforce grooming standards; refusal to comply will result in a charge of failing to follow procedure, as well as the area found not within grooming standards being shaved clean.

  [italic]OOC Note: Character appearance is a significant part of roleplay and can greatly impact a player's experience. For this reason, if you choose to enforce grooming standards, you must allow the player to adjust their own hairstyle to one that fits within grooming standards. Only if they refuse to choose one, you may give them a complete shave.[/italic]

  ## Vehicle and Motorised Assets
    If a vehicle or other general motorised asset is deployed for any reason, the following regulations apply.
      - The Commander or Adjutant may override any decisions relating to vehicle or other motorised assets.
      - Authority over ground vehicles (including tanks, Humvees, APCs, and similar assets) rests with the Vehicle Commander. If no Vehicle Commander is assigned, responsibility defaults to the Engineering Officer.
      - Authority over air vehicles rests with pilots, followed by the rest of the flight crew if no pilot is assigned.
      - Anyone may operate APCs, tanks, IFVs, and similar vehicles, provided they are capable of using the vehicle and have permission from either the Vehicle Commander, Engineering Officer, Adjutant, or Commander, and so long as operating the vehicle does not breach any deployment SOP.
      - Medical and Logistics staff may utilise a vehicle for medical frontline duties or resupplying troops on the frontline, provided it does not violate their deployment SOPs. Only one member of either department may operate or occupy the vehicle at any given time for this purpose (EX. a single doctor in a medical APC treating wounded on the frontline, or a single logistics staff member in a Humvee delivering supplies to the frontline).
      - Synthetics may be utilised as drivers but never as gunners for a vehicle.
      - Command staff may utilise vehicles so long as it does not violate their deployment SOP’s.
      - Command staff may utilise the Command type ARC for deployment to the FOB and, with the commander's permission utilize it in deployment to the frontline.

  ## Deployment Regulations
    - Medical, Requisitions, Brig, Ordnance Workshop and CIC must have at least one member of their department on the ship/installation for any other members of their department to deploy.
    - The CMO, CMP, LO and Warden may never deploy to the FOB and never to the frontline unless the ship/installation is overrun.
    - For deployment of staff, the FOB must be declared secure. If it is breached or comes under significant hostile threat, all deployed personnel are to immediately return to the ship or primary installation.

  ### Medical Staff
    - Doctors, nurses, and any other medical staff who are not the CMO may deploy to the FOB with the permission of the CMO or Commander and only to the frontline if they are within a vehicle.
    - They are not to operate the vehicle in any capacity and are to remain inside the vehicle at all times; only in the event of danger may they flee from within it.

  ### Requisitions Staff
    - Auxiliary technicians and other requisition staff who are not the LO may deploy to the FOB with the permission of the LO or Commander and only to the frontline if they are within a vehicle.
    - They may operate the vehicle and leave the vehicle, but should only do so in the delivery of supplies and remain within view of their vehicle at all times.

  ### Flight Crew
    - Flight crew may deploy freely to the FOB, but are never to deploy to the frontline

  ### Ordnance Technicians
    - Ordnance technicians may deploy to the FOB with the permission of the EO or Commander.

  ### Synthetic Units
    - Auxiliary Synthetics may deploy freely to the FOB and to the frontline
    - Working Joes are never to be deployed as they will lose connection to APOLLO and cease to function.

  ### Military Police
    - Military Police and any other Police Staff who are not the CMP may deploy to the FOB with the permission of the CMP or Commander and only to the frontline if they are performing a field arrest.

  ### Command Staff
    - The Commander may never deploy unless the ship/installation has been overrun. 
    - The Adjutant may only ever deploy to the FOB and frontline with permission from the Commander
    - The Engineering Officer may deploy freely to the FOB and never to the frontline.
    - The Intelligence Officer may deploy freely and to the frontline, but not for combat purposes, only for gathering intelligence, communication to CIC, or to act as a squad leader.
    - Junior Officers may only deploy to the FOB with permission from the Commander and if the FOB has, at a minimum, a working Phone and an Overwatch console.
    - Advisors may deploy freely to the FOB and never to the frontline.
    - If any member of the command staff were to become permanently deceased during operations, all command staff are to withdraw from deployment.
</Document>
